Guide to the Elithe Hamilton Kirkland Papers
The Wittliff Collections
Elithe Hamilton Kirkland Papers
1910-1992
1940-1992
The Wittliff Collections https://www.thewittliffcollections.txstate.edu
Kirkland, Elithe Hamilton
SWWC.030
30 Linear Feet
61 boxes
Correspondence, drafts, typescripts, photographs, scrapbooks, artifacts, ephemera and clippings document the writing career of Texas Women's Hall of Fame writer, Elithe Hamilton Kirkland.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, drafts, typescripts, photographs, scrapbooks, artifacts, ephemera and clippings constitute this collection. The bulk of this material was created by Elithe Hamilton Kirkland, although a small amount was created or maintained by her son, James Beal, the donor of this collection. (For example, documents related to Ms. Kirkland's funeral, located in box 446, folder 7, were donated by Mr. Beal.) Drafts, notes, and correspondence in this collection document Kirkland's writing process, including published and unpublished works. Many working drafts of Kirkland's published work, as well as a wealth of unpublished poems, songs, plays, short stories, and essays are included. For her published works, working drafts are accompanied by notes, publicity material, and correspondence, rounding out the evolution of these works. For much of the correspondence related to and filed with specific published works, the carbon copies of Kirkland's letters are interfiled.
Her personal history is documented as well, through formats including awards, photographs, correspondence, scrapbooks, and resumes. Highlights include long runs of correspondence between Kirkland and her mother, her son, and her husband, Dr. R.D. Kirkland. Photographs document her life from childhood through her last years, including colleagues, friends, favorite dogs, and family members.
Kirkland's interest in J. Frank Dobie is also well represented here. Her first contact with Dobie is identified as a college paper written for Dobie's graduate class at UT Austin (see box 15 folder 6a). Her novel, Heather, For Luck, is a tribute to the Texas author, and the research and drafts for this book are located in the Books series. Correspondence with Dobie, articles written by and about Dobie, books inscribed to Kirkland from Dobie, can all be found in the J. Frank Dobie series. Kirkland helped develop the first Dobie Day, celebrated at Southwestern University, in Georgetown, TX; her research and correspondence related to this effort are also located in the J. Frank Dobie series.
Resumes, career summaries, autobiographical sketches are located in this series, as are school scrapbooks and Kirkland's booklet of favorite clippings and poems. Kirkland's extensive notes and subject files are included in this Personal series, recording the breadth of her interests. Material related to her many speaking engagements is also included.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by James Beal, 1998.
Related Materials
Additional Kirkland materials in the Southwestern Writers Collection can be found in the Nancie Austin Papers (Collection 036).
Additional Elithe Hamilton Kirkland papers can also be found at Texas A & M University at Commerce, in the James G. Gee Library.
Biographical Notes
Perhaps best known for her bestselling historical romance novel, Love Is a Wild Assault, Elithe Hamilton Kirkland was also a poet, songwriter, playwright, schoolteacher, and journalist. She was born a third generation Texan in 1907, in Coleman, Texas. Both sets of her grandparents were pioneers. Her father was a farmer, and Ms. Kirkland grew up riding a horse to Coleman's one teacher schoolhouse. She was very active in her high school years, participating in the Silver Valley School District debate team, and graduating as Salutatorian in 1924. She then went on to study English and history at North Texas State University, in Denton, Texas, where she received her B.A. and her Teacher's Certificate in 1928.
Kirkland then began her career in writing and teaching with a series of jobs which included teaching high school and writing for newspapers, often at the same time, through the 1930s. From 1928-1929, Kirkland taught high school English, drama, and journalism at Mineral Wells, Texas. At the Coleman Democrat-Voice, Coleman, TX, from 1929-1930, she edited news, features, the editor's front page column, and headlines, many of which dealt with the oil boom and bank robberies. In 1930, Kirkland served as Features writer for the Brady Standard, Brady, TX, researching and photographing major farm and ranch projects in McCulloch County. Also during this time period, from 1930-1932, she taught high school English and journalism in Crane, TX, a ranching center and oil boom town. In 1935, Kirkland served as the Austin correspondent for the Dallas based Texas Weekly. From 1935-1936, she was the State Director of School Publicity (for the Texas Commission for Centennial Celebrations), authoring pamphlets on Texas history and editing the songbook, Songs Texas Sings. From 1937-1939, she was a high school teacher in the State Laboratory School, Iraan, TX, teaching speech arts, journalism, and script writing for radio. Also while at Iraan, she was state correspondent in West Texas for the Fort Worth Star Telegram, writing news stories, often centering on the oil boom.
In 1931, Kirkland married Roy Folk Beal, an interior decorator. A year later, Kirkland's only son was born, James Benjamin Beal. This marriage ended in divorce in 1936. During the summers 1938 of 1939, and during the long term 1939-1940, she was Curriculum Assistant in Department of Educational Administration at the University of Texas at Austin, working with the state on high school curriculum revision. She also attended UT Austin, studying under J. Frank Dobie, and writing a folk-drama series for the Texas State (Radio) Network which was narrated by Dobie. In 1940, she earned a Masters degree from UT Austin in English and Educational Administration.
In the 1940s, Kirkland continued her work as a print journalist, and became very involved in radio journalism. She was the Austin correspondent for the business and financial section of the The Dallas Times Herald, also writing business articles under the name L.E. Hamilton.
From 1940-1947, she was a script writer and acting director for UT Austin's radio department, Radio House, and wrote more than 500 dramatic documentaries for state and national radio networks, many of which were broadcast live from the studios on campus. At the time, Radio House was considered the only complete radio production facility in the southwest. Kirkland traveled to Mexico, among other places, to pursue stories. It was during her tenure at Radio House that Kirkland covered the story of Nazi intrigue surrounding Peck Woodside, an American pilot and businessman in Mexico, a story she would return to again and again over the years.
In 1944, she was the associate editor of Southwest Review, a quarterly publication of University Press in Dallas at Southern Methodist University.
In 1946, she wrote educational film scripts for the Commission on Motion Pictures in New Haven, Conn., including the films "Now is the Seedtime", on Tom Paine, and "Man with a Mission", on Samuel Gompers. In 1948, she married Dr. R. D. (Roy Defoe) Kirkland, an osteopathic surgeon. Also in this year, she mailed her short story "The Realm of Silence" to Pearl Buck, who praised it but described it as ahead of its time and not yet commercially viable. In fact, this story did not come to light until 1984, when it was published as the ending of her novel, The Edge of Disrepute.
As she turned her attention toward creative writing, Kirkland chose Evelyn Oppenheimer, of Dallas, as her literary agent. Oppenheimer helped direct Kirkland to writing historical romance, a genre in which Kirkland would write bestselling novels. Two of these were published in the 1950s, Divine Average(1952) and Love Is A Wild Assault, (1959), the latter being included in A. C. Greene's The 50 Best Books on Texas.
A prolific writer, Kirkland also wrote short stories, songs, poetry, musical dramas, speeches, and television scripts, on a variety of subjects. While her novels tended to be historical romances set in the Republic of Texas era, her other work reflects her broad interests in folk traditions and in the future. She described herself as a "futurist", and often wrote about space travel and parapsychology. She was a member of the Texas State Historical Association, and the national non-denominational Spiritual Frontiers Fellowship of Laymen and Clergymen. In 1982, her short story involving alien kidnapping, The Disappearance of Widow Ellen, was published in a collection of short stories by Texas women writers called Her Work, (Bryan, Texas: Shearer Publishing, 1982).
In 1984, Kirkland's last novel, The Edge of Disrepute, was published. In the next year, her husband, Dr. R.D. Kirkland, passed away, and she moved out of Austin to Wimberley. She published "Leet's Christmas", a Christmas short story including songs and verse. Kirkland remained a very sought after speaker, speaking around the state on the "Texas Voices" program for the Texas Sesquicentennial, as well as for groups such as Daughters of the American Revolution, MENSA, East Texas State University, and Western Writers of America.
In January 1987, her musical drama entitled Precious Memories was performed at the White Elephant in Fort Worth, TX, in collaboration with the Hip Pocket Theater and the Salt Lick Foundation. Kirkland wrote both the drama and lyrics, and acted as narrator. Shortly thereafter, her musical drama, Hear the Flute: An Untold Story of the Civil War in the Western Territories, was performed. Kirkland wrote the script and lyrics, Conrad Fath wrote the music.
On Nov. 12, 1987, Kirkland was inducted into Texas Women's Hall of Fame, one of many honors she received during her lifetime. Kirkland died at her home in Wimberly on Jan. 2, 1992, and was buried in her family cemetery at the David Allen Ranch known as "New Tracks", near the Blanco River, in Kyle, Texas.
Index Terms
Subjects
Historical fiction; Women authors, American -- Texas -- 20th century; Dramatists -- Texas; Historians -- Texas
Places
Women poets
Subjects (Persons)
Kirkland, Elithe Hamilton; Dobie, J. Frank (James Frank), 1888-1964
- Books, 1937-1990
  Series Description
  Arranged in alphabetical order by book title, this subseries includes research material, notes, outlines, drafts, correspondence, publicity documents, and drafts of stage and film adaptations.
  - Divine Average, 1952
    - Outline (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Typescripts: Introductory material, and Chapter V (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Character lists (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Notes, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Songs (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Summaries (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Author's annotated copy of book, including correspondence with Kirkland's mother, and with Oren J. Nicholas (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Stage treatment (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Motion picture treatment (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Copyright information (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Contract with Little, Brown and Co. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Publicity: photographs and blurbs - Little Brown and Co. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Clippings (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence with and clippings regarding Walter Prescott Webb, Divine Average (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Toego (horse) documents (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - The Edge of Disrepute, 1984
    - Typewritten uncorrected draft (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
    - Early material on Sarah Belle (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Clippings (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Critical acclaim (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Publicity - Shearer Publishing, Barbara Whitehead (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Heather for Luck, undated
    - Working draft, arranged by chapters (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
    - Typewritten drafts with corrections (Box 3, Folder 3-6)
  - Love Is a Wild Assault, 1959
    - Outline (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Chapter Summary Drafts (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Chapter Drafts - Chapters I through IV (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Chapter Drafts - Unused Epilogue by George Salmon (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Source material on Potters - Hall, Nell. "The History of Harriet A. Ames During the Early Days of Texas", Thesis, East Texas State Teachers College, August 1941 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Source material on Potters - Potter, Robert. "Address to the People of Granville Co." Robert Potter, 1832. (photocopy) (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Research Notes
      - Alamo description (unused) (Box 4, Folder 6a)
      - Caddo Equivalent for "The Perfect One" (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Harriet's Account (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - Harriet's demise and New Orleans (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - Peter Sky (Box 4, Folder 10)
      - Regulator / Moderator War and the Neutral Strip (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - San Jacinto, Nacogdoches, Red River, Texas Navy (Box 4, Folder 12)
      - Snake Seecher and Miscellany of Notation (Box 4, Folder 13)
      - Supreme Court (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Poem - A Salute to Houston (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Contracts - Doubleday and Avon, and foreign publishers, also including royalty statements and copyright information, correspondence with Evelyn Oppenheimer, 1966-1983 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Publicity - Doubleday and Avon (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Speeches and Programs, 1950-1967 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      Contents
      Texas State Historical Association, Austin, TX, April 1955
      Nicholson Memorial Library, Garland, TX April 1967
      Lecture and Harriet Sketch, Kyle, TX, October 1967
      Westwood Country Club, undated
      Unidentified location, November 1967
    - Scripts - Television and Film - Correspondence (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Scripts - Television and Film - Drafts (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence
      - A (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - Asbury, Samuel (Box 5, Folder 8)
      - B-C (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - D (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - Doubleday (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Dwan, Alan (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - E-L (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - M-N (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - Montgomery, Marg-Riette (Daughters of the Republic of Texas) (Box 6, Folder 7)
      - Norvell, Judge James R. (Box 6, Folder 8)
      - O-P (Box 6, Folder 9)
      - Oppenheimer, Evelyn, 1967-1977 (Box 6, Folder 10)
      - Q-S (Box 6, Folder 11)
      - Stuart, Malcolm (literary agent) (Box 6, Folder 12)
      - T-Z (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Middlebusters (partial novel), 1937
    - Chapter drafts (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, including critique from J. Frank Dobie (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Peck Woodside's World War I Adventure (see also Guardians of Freedom radio series in Series 5), 1990
    - First draft (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Second draft (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Research material (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Notes (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Photographs/Maps (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Peck Woodside autobiographical sketch (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Final version: "The Private War of Peck Woodside: Nazi Intrigue in the Jungles of Mexico" (2 copies) (Box 7, Folder 9-10)
  - Trellis of Memory, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Unspoken Love: A Historical Novel, undated
    - Drafts (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
    - Notes (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Musicals, 1969-1990
  Arranged in alphabetical order by the name of the musical, this subseries includes drafts, notes and correspondence documenting the creation and production of Kirkland's musicals.
  - "Devil's Backbone" (Lyrics by Conrad Fath) (Originally titled "The Uphillers" in 1969, and also known as "Cedar Choppers", this musical comedy was worked into its final form and named "Devil's Backbone" and copyrighted in 1974.), 1969-1990
    - Research material (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Notes (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Outlines (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Prospectus (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Drafts (incomplete) (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Stage presentation (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Bound version of prospectus and stage presentation (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - "Hear the Flute", circa 1970-1990
    - Research material
      - Diary of Hervey Alexander Adams, with Kirkland's notes (Box 9, Folder 9)
      - Diary of Hervey Alexander Adams, 1842-43, with introduction by Kirkland (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - Hervey Alexander Adams genealogy research, 1979 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - General research (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Notes (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Drafts (Box 10, Folder 5-6, Box 11)
    - Final bound copies (Box 12, Folder 1-3)
    - Synopsis (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Entire work (Box 12, Folder 5-6)
    - Music and lyrics only (Box 13, Folder 2-3)
    - Audiocassette of music (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Copyright (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Clippings / Photographs (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - "The Merry Monk", undated (Box 13, Folder 7a)
  - "Mr. Magnet", 1979
    - Draft (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Typescript (carbon copy) (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Research materials (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Notes (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - "Precious Memories", 1985-1986
    - Background research - Iraan, TX (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Background research - Salt Lick Singers (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Clippings (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Drafts (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Notes (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Photographs (undated performance) (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Program/Poster (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Publicity (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - Scripts (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - "Rehearsal repair script" (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - Production script (partial) (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - Worksheets (Box 14, Folder 17)
- Essays and Articles, 1918-1990
  Material in this subseries includes essays written for college classes, and articles written for newspapers. Some published, many are unpublished. They are arranged in alphabetical order, with a special section for Kirkland's freshman year college papers.
  - Correspondence / Rejection letters for articles, including EHK's carbons of outgoing mail, 1956 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - All Is Vanity (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Barton Springs Reading (Mt. Bonnell Inspired) (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - By Way of Illustration (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Called to Silver Valley (West Texas Sketch), 1990 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - College Papers (Freshman Year) (Box 15, Folder 6)
    The Advantage of Reading Historical Novels
    A History Recitation in a Rural School
    How I Write My Freshman Themes
    The Most Thrilling Time I Ever Had
    My Acquaintance With Hard Luck
    My Dogs
    A Serious Problem
    Vandals and Vandalism
    What I Should Do If I Had Lots of Money and All the Time I Needed
  - David Crockett: Candidate for Reelection (written in Dobie's class at UT Austin, EHK's first contact with Dobie) (Box 15, Folder 6a)
  - Depression Story, 1932-1933 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Dishes Bought in Peters' Colony Are Still in Use (Dallas Morning News), November 19, 1933 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Dry River: A Sketch of Hard Times, 1933 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Finish of The Durrum Twins (or Murder at the Microphone) (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - If I Make My Bed in Hell: Account of OJ's Dream (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - It Can Be Done (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - The Lazy Farmer (with rejection letter from H.L. Mencken) (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - Mad Scientist Interview (Box 15, Folder 13a)
  - McCulloch County's Oldest Living Pioneer... (The Brady Standard, Brady Texas, June 24, 1930 (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - McMahan, Mary E.: Personal Feature (Box 15, Folder 15)
  - Organic School (first assignment in a series of articles for the Dallas Morning News), 1925 (Box 15, Folder 16)
  - Serpent in the Garden (Burnet Mine Exp.) (Box 15, Folder 17)
  - "Shootin' Wild" West Texas Incident (Box 15, Folder 18)
  - Texas Jigsaw Outline (for Big Staging) (Box 15, Folder 19)
  - Walker, Stanley - article in Austin-American Statesman, February 17, 1918 (Box 15, Folder 20)
  - The Wondrous Mirror (Episcopal Church history), 1953 (Box 15, Folder 21)
- Poetry, 1944-1988, undated
  Although Kirkland never officially published her poetry on its own, it appears in her novels and short stories. For many years, her Christmas cards featured her Christmas poems which are listed here in chronological order by year. Also of particular interest is a one-of-a- kind handmade booklet of Kirkland's war poems written for World War II soldiers. Poems listed with quotation marks represent the first line of untitled poems.
  - An Appeal to La Cima (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Astral Memories (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - At Twenty-Five (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Autumn Delight (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Beautiful Moments (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Birthright (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - This Is My Birthday, January 24, 1978 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - The Chasm: A Dream (see also Dream Notes: The Chasm) (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Christmas Poems, 1944-1988, undated
    - "Greetings from a Friend Like You...", 1944 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Apology at Yuletide, 1946 (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - "'It's plain to see,' one wise man said...", 1947 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - "Hallowed Be His Day of Birth...", 1948 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - "God of Wisdom, God of Truth...", 1950 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - The Measure, 1951 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Starlight and Storm, 1952 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - "I choose to give you, friend, with love and pleasure...", 1953 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Star Symbol, 1954 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Of Such Is the Kingdom, 1955 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Christmas Angel, 1956 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - The Guiding Thread, 1957 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Christmas Picture, The Flute and The Lyre, And the Wonder Is, 1651 at the Palace Gate (incomplete), 1963 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Full Moon at Monte Alban (including correspondence and research regarding poem set in Oaxaca, Mexico), 1988 (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - Season of Gifts, "The Christ's Birthday, the sacred night...", "This Christmas Day Will Pass Away...", The Dance Divine, Glimpse of the Kingdom, Light Life Love, undated (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - Christmas poems from EHK to Dr. RDK, undated (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Come, Come from the Mist (Box 16, Folder 14)
  - Concept Audile (Hear, Mr. President) (Box 16, Folder 15)
  - Confession in Verse (Box 16, Folder 16)
  - The Dance Divine (Box 16, Folder 17)
  - Did You Ever Hear a Tree Talking? Well I Did! (Mesquite poem) (Box 16, Folder 18)
  - Don't You Call Me Sweetheart (Box 16, Folder 19)
  - Dreams (Box 16, Folder 20)
  - Eternal Truth (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Exceptional Mary (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Fairy of Fancy (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - February (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - A Floral Salute (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - The Flower Princess (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - For Charles and Sandra Schiller (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - For Conrad and Shudde Fath (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - For Penny James (Born to the Space Age) (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - For Robert Lamar Boyd, Jr.: Your Heritage (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Freedom From Want (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - From the Avil (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - A Good Man Can Never Die (Box 17, Folder 13)
  - The Great Hoax of '43 (Box 17, Folder 14)
  - He Thought (Box 17, Folder 15)
  - High Priestess of the Temple (Box 17, Folder 16)
  - I Am Tired (Box 17, Folder 17)
  - "I brought something down from the mountain..." (Box 17, Folder 18)
  - "I do not care for streets of gold..." (Box 17, Folder 19)
  - I Have a Picture in My Mind (Box 17, Folder 20)
  - "I like a man with guts and brains!..." (Box 17, Folder 21)
  - I Love You with an Old Love (Box 17, Folder 22)
  - I Shall Write a Poem (Box 17, Folder 23)
  - I Wear Your Rose (Box 17, Folder 24)
  - Light-Sight (Box 17, Folder 25)
  - Love Is A Robber (Box 17, Folder 26)
  - Marriage (Box 17, Folder 27)
  - Mixed Up (Box 17, Folder 27a)
  - Morning Sun Is Glory (Box 17, Folder 28)
  - Mother (Box 17, Folder 29)
  - Mother Love (Box 17, Folder 30)